A Guide to the Atcheson L. Hench Autograph Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Collection of Modern Autographs
  - 1908 August 19 John Singleton Mosby (1833-1916) to Major [Eben] Swift, sends him "a volume of war reminiscences which originally were some fugitive sketches I wrote for The Boston Herald that were afterward collected & put into book form: the last chapter is an address I delivered at … Boston," and an article by him on Gettysburg in Belford's Magazine (1891) describing briefly his theory of the campaign, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:14)
  - 1908 August 24 John Singleton Mosby (1833-1916) to Major [Eben] Swift, speaks of his "closest call" during the Civil War when he was wounded at Lake's house on December 21, 1864; and sends a scrapbook containing the piece he wrote about it, a set of highly valued books, an article "By a Stratagem," and a copy of a letter he wrote to Judge Keith of the Virginia Court of Appeals. 1 page, with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 10:14)
  - 1909 November 8 John Singleton Mosby (1833-1916) to Major [Eben] Swift, disagrees with his article in the Journal about the objective of [Alfred?] Pleasonton's attacks on Stuart at Brandy Station which he believed was to break up Stuart's camp and drive him over the Rapidan, 1 page, with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 10:14)
  - 1889 March 23 John Singleton Mosby (1833-1916) to General Marcus Joseph Wright (1831-1922) answers Wright's question about the accuracy of a statement in Appleton's Encyclopedia of Biography about Mosby first published in The New York Herald in July or August of 1876, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:15)
  - [1914 July 20] John Singleton Mosby (1833-1916) Autograph and small photograph (as an old man) on a card; other signatures and photographs on the card include: Fountain Beattie (1841-1923), Lycurgus Hutchison, and George Turberville; includes related material (6435) (Box-folder 10:16)
  - 1865 May 13 John Ware Mosby, uncle of John Singleton Mosby, to George S. Palmer, informs him that "Jack has consented for me to send the bearer to Richmond to see what terms he can be paroled upon and to find out whether they intend any prosecution against him." He wants Mosby to take care of these matters and return to practicing Law, but stresses that "It is necessary for him to have a safe conduct so as he can go in and take his parole from General Halleck in whose name he wishes it, as there is so large a reward offered for him from a lesser authority it might not be observed, his having disbanded his men it shows he has discontinued hostilities." 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:17)
  - 1842 May V[ictoria] P. M[osby], [sister of John Singleton Mosby] to Miss Henrianne Cabell [Early] (1822-1890), writes that she did not make it to Betty Brown's wedding, has not had Add [Callaway?] to see her yet although she invited many from the family to meet her, mentions other socials engagements and begs her to come and visit with her, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:18)
  - 1842 February 22 V[ictoria] P. M[osby], [sister of John Singleton Mosby] to Mrs. Sally M. Ward, mentions Mr. Friend's wedding, Betty Brown's engagement might be broken off, Rosalie Pollard is quite the belle in Richmond, Mrs. Henderson is well received in society in Richmond, Robert Brown is to marry one of the Miss Callaways, either Elvira or Sarah, her happiness at having Add and Carrington Callaway as neighbors soon, busy reading Charles Dickens, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:19)
  - 1906 May 15 Fridtjof Nansen (1861-1930) to Mr. Fraser, thanks him for sending the manuscript for him to see and correct, saying "Your description of myself made me blush you have to take that on your own responsibility." 1 page (6435-w) (Box-folder 10:20)
  - 1898 February 20 Fridtjof Nansen (1861-1930) to Major James Burton Pond (1838-1903), thanks him for his kind letter and discusses his successful lecture tour in England which surpassed his expectations, 2 pages on 1 l. with envelope (6435-aj) (Box-folder 10:21)
  - 1823 April 23 Robert Nares (1753-1829) to Thomas Cadell (1773-1836), the Younger, with Cadell's reply, May 9, 1823, on the same leaf; refers to the proofs wanted for the completion of Macklin's Bible that he sent to Cadell about a month ago, wanting renewed advertising of his remarks on the improved version, and remarking on the current hard times for clergy; Cadell assures Nares that he has received the proofs, has placed advertising in several papers, and will attempt to sell the remaining 508 copies through booksellers by trade sale; 3 pages on 1 l., with an engraving of Nares (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:22)
  - 1939 April 30 Allan Nevins (1890-1971) to H.T. Newcomb, writes that John Reed's disillusionment with the Russian revolution and communism prior to his death is well established and thanks Newcomb for bringing Mr. Rubin's book to his attention, 1 typewritten page (6435-av) (Box-folder 10:23)
  - 1802 March 13 John Nicholas (1761-1819) to James Rees, approves his arrangements for a house, but chiefly concerns a "mill scheme" involving the damming of a lake at Geneva, New York, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-aj) (Box-folder 10:24)
  - 1903 March 7 Yone Noguchi (1875-1947) to Madison Cawein (1865-1914) writes about a time when he was staying with Joaquin Miller on his glorious California hill and after supper a guitar was produced and Noguchi read from Cawein's book of poetry as they wandered under the stars. Currently he is wandering in England. Noguchi also expresses his happiness that Cawein liked his pamphlet and that his own new book of poems is coming out in ten days., 3 pages on 2 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:25)
  - 1886 July 28 Charles Eliot Norton (1827-1908) to Mrs. Bond, arranges for her to make more copies of letters for him, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:26)
  - 1887 December 10 Charles Eliot Norton (1827-1908) to Charles H. Brooks, informs him that he knows nothing of Henry D. Norton, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:27)
  - 1887 May 21 Charles Eliot Norton (1827-1908) to Mrs. Dickinson, sends her his autograph as an expression of his sympathy and good will, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:28)
  - 1881 July 20 Charles Eliot Norton (1827-1908) to "Dear Miss Emerson" sends a letter of introduction for Edwin D. Mead, author of a book on the philosophy of Carlyle, who wishes to meet her father, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:29)
  - 1887 June 30 Charles Eliot Norton (1827-1908) to Dana Estes (1840-1909?), publisher, thanks him for the return of Fletcher's letter about an archaeological case in Cotrone, Italy, Calabria region, about which he states, "The circumstances of the case were not exactly such as Mr. Fletcher supposes. Whether Baron Berlingieri's and Mr. Clarke's procedures at Cotrone were contrary to the laws valid in Calabria is, I believe, to be determined by judicial investigation and decision." He also wishes him success in finding the results of the excavations of the Etruscan tombs, 3 pages on 1 l. Norton was the first president of The Archaeological Institute of America, 1879-90. (6435) (Box-folder 10:30)
  - 1900 November 10 Charles Eliot Norton (1827-1908) to Mr. Hart, thanks him for the copy of his paper on the past twenty years of the life of their college [Harvard], 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:31)
  - 1866 May 23 Charles Eliot Norton (1827-1908) to C[harles] C[reighton] Hazewell (1814-1883), asks him to write a critical notice of Mr. Towles's Henry V for the North American Review, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:32)
  - 1864 December 10 Charles Eliot Norton (1827-1908) to Oliver Johnson (1809-1889), encloses payment for a subscription to The Antislavery Standard for L.A.O. of Martinsville Ohio, who has an extract of their letter in the current number of the paper, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:33)
  - 187[9?] February 26 Charles Eliot Norton (1827-1908) to the Reverend Dr. [Andrew Preston?] Peabody (1811-1893), furnishes a reference for Miss Allatt as a French teacher, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:34)
  - 1907 March 14 Charles Eliot Norton (1827-1908) to Mrs. C.B. Perkins, accepts her apologies for the misadventure with the portfolio and absolves her of blame, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:35)
  - 1897 January 11 Charles Eliot Norton (1827-1908) to Miss Minna Smith, writes that he is sorry to hear of her illness and hopes to have a visit from her soon, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:36)
  - 1902 May 20 Charles Eliot Norton (1827-1908) to the Honorable Winslow Warren (1838-1930), thanks him for the copy of his review of Governor Taft's evidence, saying "What a national blessing a little financial calamity would be!", 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:37)
  - 1867 August 3 Charles Eliot Norton (1827-1908) to "My dear Sir," thanks him for his "able and interesting paper on George III" for The North American Review and engages him for additional work, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:38)
  - 1803, 1805 John Page (1744-1808), Governor of Virginia, signature on four land grants to James Gray, Joseph Nichols, John London, and Pleasant Story, assignee of John London, all on vellum with seals, oversize (6435)
  - 1902 October 19 Walter Hines Page (1855-1918) to Hollis [?], writes about the desire of his son, Ralph W. Page, to be an engineer and asks for his advice on how his son should prepare for that career, 6 pages on 2 l. (6435-ax) (Box-folder 10:39)
  - 1882 April 22 Sir James Paget, (1814-1899) to "Dear Mr. Hill," chooses the date of June 13th [for his talk?] 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:40)
  - 1863 January 19 Coventry Kersey Dighton Patmore (1823-1896) to Louis Dickinson, declines his invitation to his Saturday evening events because he rarely goes out since the death of his wife his is occupied entirely with the care of his children in the evenings and is dull company as well, 2 pages on 1 l., on mourning stationery (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:41)
  - 1904 January 13 Andrew Henry Patterson (1870-1928), University of Georgia, to [William Lloyd] Garrison (1838-1909), apologizes for the long delay in answering his letter; thanks him for the copy of The World's Work; discusses in great detail and at length his views of the various classes of the "Negro race" in the South; disagrees with him that a "resident white Southerner in good standing cannot do work with and among Negroes without exciting suspicion and losing caste" citing the examples of William A. Blair and Henry E. Fries at the Slater School with Professor Atkins, Salem, North Carolina; expresses surprise at his statement that it was not wrong for slaves to steal from their masters; addresses Garrison's opinion that Southerners treated aged ex-slaves kindly only out of a troubled conscience; expresses a paternalistic attitude "The feeling of the better class of Southern whites for the Negroes is much the feeling of older persons for children, and our feeling toward the rising generation of Negroes is much the same as that of older persons toward [pert?], disagreeable, spoiled children"; he also tackles the topics of servant's wages, rape of black or mulatto women, justice in the courtroom, and his belief that Negroes are "members of a race without a past, with little hope of a future, - a race dwelling on the very edge of the evolutionary stream of the world's history.", 10 pages on 5 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:42)
  - 1934 March 31 Governor George C. Peery (1873-1952) to M.E. Gilfond, encloses a letter to Congressman Sol Bloom at his request (not present), 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:43)
  - 1804 February 24 Bishop Thomas Percy (1729-1811), Bishop of Dromore, to the Reverend John Blakeway, apologizes for the delay in answering his letter due to an eye complaint; writes that they are in a part of Ireland hopefully not likely to be the first scene of the French Invasion [by Napoleon] and is within a few miles of three seaports all pointing to Scotland or England, if he should land as he did in 1798, 4 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:44)
  - 1903 April 21 Bliss Perry (1860-1954) to Mrs. Charles E. St. John, declines her invitation to the luncheon of the Smith College Alumnae due to a prior engagement, 1 typewritten page (6435-az) (Box-folder 10:45)
  - n.d. Wendell Phillips (1811-1884) to [Edwin Percy] Whipple (1819-1886), returns the Macaulay item with thanks, resisting temptation, and cites the source for a quotation that had eluded them earlier, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:46)
  - 1821 July 26 John Pickering (1777-1846) to James Savage (1784-1873), sends fourteen pages of the proposed Preface to Eliot's Grammar and plans to send ten or twelve pages more on Monday containing "a little investigation of the dialects spoken in New England" and makes arrangements for the remainder of the printing work to be done on the new edition, [The Indian Grammar begun; or, an Essay to bring the Indian Language into Rules, for the help of such as desire to learn the same, for the furtherance of the Gospel among them. By John Eliot, Reprinted, with Notes and Observations by John Pickering and Duponceau, in: Collections of the Massachusetts Historical Society, Second Series, Vol. IX. dated Boston, 1822, 8vo. Contains: Pp. 223 - 242, the Massachusetts Language: Introductory Observations, by John Pickering; dated Salem, July, 1821. Pp. 243-312, reprint of Eliot's Grammar. Pp. (313 - 341) i - xxix, Notes and Observations on Eliot's Grammar. Addressed to John Pickering, by Petee Duponceau. Pp. (342 - 36D) xxx - xlviii, Supplementary Observations, by the Editor. Pp. (361-366), xlix - liv, Index of Indian Words in Eliot's Grammar; including Select Words from his Translation of the Bible.], 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:47)
  - 1919 September 4 Gifford Pinchot (1865-1946) to B.L. Young, sends a form letter to thank him for being a member of the National Conservation Association for ten years, 1 typewritten page (6435-av) (Box-folder 10:48)
  - 1798 May-June Receipts to John McLeod, John L. Taylor, and Caleb Swan for bateaus to Fort Washington on the Ohio River, Cincinnati, and repairs and other work, from the United States [Military?], Pittsburgh, 3 receipts (6435) (Box-folder 10:49)
  - 1837 November 27 James Madison Porter (1793-1862), Secretary of War under President Tyler, to George Pearson, Secretary of the Diagnothian Literary Society, Marshall College, Mercersburg, Pennsylvania, Porter expresses his sense of honor at being made a member of the Society, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:50)
  - 1890 December 20 J.W. Porter, Charlottesville, Virginia, to W.P. St.John, has written Senators Plumb, Allison, and Stewart, about his pleas for financial relief, and discusses their concerns about the appreciated fluctuating dollar and other economic woes, "American labor will surely revolt before submitting to European conditions. Farmers are reduced now to the verge of ruin, and vast numbers are already beggared by the close competition of India [bonused] by the cheap silver we sell. They are getting wild under the sense of injustice." He goes on to add a lengthy postscript about the issue of gold and silver being drained away to foreign lands., 3 pages on 2 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:51)
  - 1839 June 13 Bryan Waller Proctor [pseudonym Barry Cornwall] (1787-1874) to Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855), promises to send her some poetry for her annual if he has any raw material to draw from but must first take care of his legal business, and describes seeing Daniel Webster, "I have just met (at Mr. Kenyon's) Daniel Webster, the famous American orator. He has a broad, strongly-marked brow, with a dark, deep-set eye that looks full of intelligence and vigor. I do not remember ever to have encountered a man whose looks struck me so much. He is a little cold in his manner (like most of his countrymen in general), but it is not offensive. It is rather a grave self-possession than superciliousness.", 3 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 10:52)
  - 1867 March 20 Alexander Williams Randall (1819-1872), Postmaster General under President Johnson, signature on appointment of Henry Massie as Deputy Postmaster of Charlottesville, Virginia, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:53)
  - 1787 June 18 Beverley Randolph (1754-1797), Lt. Governor of Virginia, signature on land grant to William May, Nelson County, Virginia, on vellum, oversize (6435)
  - 1803 February 23 Mutual Assurance Society Insurance policy signed by Edmund Randolph for a house in Richmond, Virginia (6435) (Box-folder 10:54)
  - 1819 December 29 [John Randolph of Roanoke] to Mr. Skinner, requests that the unknown paper be bound from the beginning and the numbers sent to him during the session of Congress also; with a cut signature of T[homas] M[ann] Randolph glued to the letter. Folder contains a note concerning a collector's confusion of the two Randolphs and the pasting of this signature to the letter, 1 page, copy, original in Vault- John Randolph of Roanoke (6435) (Box-folder 10:55)
  - [n.y.] January 5 John Randolph to Stephen Van Rensselear, asks him to dine with him next Tuesday when he will also enjoy the company of [Harmanus] Bleecker, 1 page, copy, original in Vault- John Randolph of Roanoke (6435) (Box-folder 10:56)
  - 1782 July 21 Thomas Mann Randolph, Sr. (1741-1793) to Messrs. Cohen Isaacs & Co., Richmond, Virginia, orders two pair of cotton cards, two of wool cards, two of their largest sized India mats, two curry combs and six ounces of alum, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:57)
  - 1789 May 15 Thomas Mann Randolph, Sr. (1741-1793) to "Dear Gentlemen" sends letter of introduction for his son, Thomas, while in New York, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:58)
  - 1791 September 29 Thomas Mann Randolph, Sr. (1741-1793) to "Dear Sirs" discusses his plans for settling his total debt with them, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:59)
  - 1817 October 26 Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr. (1768-1828) to Robert Brent, Paymaster General, U.S. Army, informs him that he has not received pay, or drawn rations or forage in kind from the United States since December 1, 1813, and seeks military compensation, believing his last paymaster to have been Colonel Fenwick in New York., 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:60)
  - 1820 December 7 Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr. (1768-1828), Governor of Virginia, signature on land grant to George Kailor, Rockingham County, Virginia, on vellum, oversize (6435)
  - 1823 December 15 Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr. (1768-1828) to Henry Remsen (1762-1843), President [Bank of the Manhattan Company?], shares his good news from the Virginia Legislature about the University of Virginia which should open next autumn and John Wickham's agreement to name appraisers for his estate on the river below and that in Albemarle to include in the mortgage. He also expresses "the very strong sentiment of gratitude to you for this most important favor to my numerous and excellent family of a wife, six daughters and five sons, which I most sincerely and warmly feel and shall ever cherish in an honest and constant heart. For myself I am altogether indifferent as to the good or evil which may be in fate for me.", 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:61)
  - n.y. April 21 Charles Reade (1814-1884) to Dear [Wilkie Collins?], writes that he is too unsettled at present to make an appointment to see his correspondent, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:62)
  - 1863 January 6 Maurice Regan, 2nd Regiment, Pennsylvania Heavy Artillery, at a camp near Fairfax Station, to Doctor Pennock, writes Pennock that they still receive the Delaware County Republican, have a good general who "studies the comfort of his men," General [Thomas Leiper?] Kane, and have left a beautiful valley near the Potomac River, where they were told they would winter. He also describes their march from camp on the Leesburg Pike, passing Hillsboro, Wheatland, and Leesburg, where all the stores and shops were closed up with the people standing on the street corners with long faces, and continuing on to Fairfax Court House, where they camped and had prayers the next morning. Next the troops experienced the discomfort of heavy rain while camping next to Occoquan Creek and many threw away their wet woolen blankets and clothing along the way. He also describes "this part of Virginia we see nothing but sad desolation and destruction, nearly the whole of Virginia lays in open commons from woods to woods we can seldom see a fence all burnt by soldiers for whenever they halt for the night they pitch in to the fences of there is any handy and in a few minutes whole fields are laid open and before morning many a cord of rails are burnt.", 8 pages on 2 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:63)
  - 1857 May 13 Anna Cora (Ogden) Mowatt Ritchie (1819-1870) to "Mr. and Mrs. James Thomas Fields (1816-1881), introduces and recommends her friend and acting pupil, Miss Avonia Jones (1836-1867, married G.V. Brooke in 1863) who she believes will make a fine actress, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:64)
  - 1856 December 15 Anna Cora (Ogden) Mowatt Ritchie (1819-1870) to "My dear Miss Pleasanton," fulfills her promise of an autograph, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:65)
  - n.d. Anna Cora (Ogden) Mowatt Ritchie (1819-1870) to "My own Darling" changes their arrangement to visit due to changes in her own schedule and mentions the "toil of posing" possibly for a portrait, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:66)
  - [1859 September 30?] Anna Cora (Ogden) Mowatt Ritchie (1819-1870) signature at the end of a passage presumably from a play, either called "Old Maid" or by a character called "Old Maid" 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:67)
  - 1865 February 22 Alfred Rives (1830-1903), Confederate War Department, Engineer Bureau, to Socrates Maupin (1808-1871), University of Virginia, Chairman of the Faculty, asks if the University has a good oxy-hydrogen blowpipe and reflector that the Engineer Bureau might purchase or borrow, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:68)
  - 1892 May 2 Amelie Rives (1863-1945) to Dr. Bleyer, invites him to lunch on the morrow and promises to have his souvenir ready, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-az) (Box-folder 10:69)
  - 1893 September 2 Amelie Rives (1863-1945) to Dr. Bleyer, congratulates him on his good fortune of late and thanks him for all his kindness, 4 pages on 1 l. (6435-l) (Box-folder 10:70)
  - [1888?] February 1 Amelie Rives (1863-1945) to W[illiam] T[homas] Moore (1832-1926), discusses the sporting slang word "gee" and says an example of its use in literature is "The Right Sort." 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:71)
  - 1889 February 21 Amelie Rives (1863-1945) to Mr. Walsh, voices her concerns about errors in the proofs for her book which must be corrected, 4 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:72)
  - 1945, n.d. Amelie Rives (1863-1945) Autograph and Quotation on a Note card, with a news clipping of her obituary, 1945, 1 page (6435-bh) (Box-folder 10:73)
  - 1848 June 10 William Cabell Rives (1793-1868) to Thomas Aspinwall (1786-1876), Consul of the United States at London, sends a letter of introduction for John Cowles, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:74)
  - 1836 June 18 William Cabell Rives (1793-1868) to E.L. Burd, offers a letter of introduction to Governor Cass, who will soon be appointed minister to Paris, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 10:75)
  - 1836 September 14 William Cabell Rives (1793-1868) to Churchill C. Cambreleng (1786-1862), entrusts a letter to him for Captain Nicolson, believed to be currently in New York, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:76)
  - 1843 April 8 William Cabell Rives (1793-1868) to Messrs. Corcoran & Riggs, Washington, encloses a check for Thomas Sewall for forty dollars which he will thank them to pay upon presentation and he will either place the same amount with their correspondent in Richmond or meet any draft that they may give upon him, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 10:77)